<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The word of the Lord to the inhabitants of Leeds</title>
            <author>Watson, Samuel, ca. 1618-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220888</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832273</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832273</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36745</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65275)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36745)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2102:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The word of the Lord to the inhabitants of Leeds</title>
                  <author>Watson, Samuel, ca. 1618-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Simmons at the sign of the Bull and Mouth near Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Samuel Watson.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Wing gives title as: "A word of the Lord ..".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Future punishment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36745:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Word of the Lord to the Inhabitants of</hi> LEEDS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>OH Inhabitants of <hi>Leeds</hi> and the adjacent places belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am burdened in ſpirit till I write unto you, and you Rulers and Prieſts thereof eſpecially ſhall know in the day of the Lords account, that I ſet not my hand to Paper till I was commanded of the Lord, the fire of whoſe jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie is kindled, though you are not yet come to the feeling of it, to burn and conſume the houſe of <hi>Eſau</hi> which is as ſtubble, that his Servant <hi>Jacob,</hi> (whom <hi>Eſau</hi> for a time Lords over) may have the Inheriance in the purchaſed poſſeſſion where none can make afraid, and to give his <hi>Iſrael</hi> reſt and deliverance from under hard-hearted <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> in bringing him even all the Seed which is but one, into the Land of uprightneſſe which flows with milk and hony, that their ſouls may be refreſhed in the green pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of love, and every one have reſt under their own vine, and rejoyce in the paths of holineſs for evermore.</p>
            <p>And this is his work notwithwanding the hardneſſe of your hearts, which in tears I expreſſe unto you, and the Lord rebuke that ſpirit which cannot believe in the ſpirit of Truth, which gives every particular who are obedient to feel after Gods Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and worſhip in Spirit and Truth, in the true ſeparation from the carnal, without which Friends you feel and enjoy, all Profeſſion is but ſandy, and building thereon; <hi>the time is haſting on a pace, that the overflowing Scourge muſt paſſe,</hi> and ſurely all thats not built upon the Rock Chriſt Jeſus will be thrown down; Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in plainneſs and in Gods Love I exhort you to conſider your ſtanding, and try what ſpirit you are of, and to what root you are grafted in, <hi>for ſuch as the tree ſuch is the fruit,</hi> if the Root be holy <hi>the branches are holy;</hi> And the viſitation of Gods Love is yet to you that you may come to the feeling after him, that not any of you who as yet are in Ignorance may periſh for want of the true Knowledge, But <hi>to you that yet ſit in darkneſs and under the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſhadow of death light may ſpring up,</hi> according to the promiſe, to work this effect, as tis witneſſed by all the Children of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>God who commanded light to ſhine out of darkneſſe hath ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36745:2"/>in our hearts, to give us the knowledge of the Glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> And this is that (the Light) which you muſt come as to a chief <hi>Corner-ſtone,</hi> which as yet is rejected by you who are of the World, as is manifeſt by your practiſe, and the day is come wherein the Lord abhors profeſſion without the life and power of godlines, <hi>and his Sword of the Spirit</hi> is drawn to cut down that wch cumbers the ground, <hi>the briars and the Thorns,</hi> which tears <hi>the fleece of the ſheep;</hi> and ſcarce would ſuffer them to live upon the earth.</p>
            <p>O People and unwiſe, do you not know that the Lord hath a controverſie with you for theſe things, and you that are in the Iniquity ſhall not eſcape puniſhnent, though you <hi>joyn hand in hand,</hi> and make many covers from the Scriptures, and plead for the Traditions and Cuſtoms of the Fathers, who lived in Ignorance as well as you, and through the profeſſion of a Law and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which was read every Sabbath day, <hi>crucified the juſt and did diſpightfully unto the Spirit of Grace,</hi> for this I ſpeak in the Truth, that your life is not according to the Scriptures nor the power of godlineſſe; So wait, be patient and conſider your errour, for in this it is partly demonſtrated by your particular acting towards me who am a witneſſe againſt your deeds. For thus it was to me, early in the morning upon the fourth day of the firſt month, the Word of the Lord came unto me, (mine eyes ſpiritually being on the Inhabitants of this place) <hi>Go ſpeak unto them, You are a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fitted for deſtruction, becauſe you believe not in that which mortifies the fleſh, the Spirit of Truth is that which mortifies the fleſh, and who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves not in this, and waits not in this, deſtruction is of themſelves; and the Steeple-houſe ſacrifice or ſervice which is external, as the Prieſts manifeſts doth not work any thing unto this, the Redemption of the Soul;</hi> And when I came into the Steeple-houſe he who is called a Paſtor or a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was expounding (as tis called) and after he had done, theſe words beforementioned came on me to ſpeak, and before I had them all uttered, they manifeſted themſelves not to be a Church but a Synagogue, according as tis Recorded in <hi>John</hi> 16. <hi>Theſe things have I ſpoken unto you that you ſhould not be offended, The time ſhall come when they ſhall caſt you out of the Synagogue,</hi> ſo they did, &amp; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but caſt <hi>me into priſon;</hi> And thou who is called the Paſtor was ſpeaking to the people <hi>that though ſome did cenſure you, yet you were to be ſo charitable as not to be violent to them, as even to ſqueeze blood out of them,</hi> or the like, and then Imediately the little effect of thy words was ſeen, for as ſoon as I had got the words of Truth ſpoken, away
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36745:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>with me to priſon; and where is your charity in this, and what is this but violence, and even to ſqueeze blood out of one, for what know you but by ſuch dealings a tender body might be deſtroyed, as ſeveral of the Innocent witneſſes of God hath been, for the Teſtimony to Truth bearing, in the Priſons of <hi>England.</hi> And alſo <hi>John Sayles</hi> thou gave forth this Doctrine to the people, to feed upon, <hi>viz. That the Miniſters work is onely to meddle with the external things, as the Sacraments and the like, and to leave the work of the Spirit to Chriſt.</hi> O thou dark Antichriſtian Miniſter, which never was made a Miniſter by God, according to the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wherein all the Miniſters of Chriſt are, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.16. <hi>I have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto thee for this purpoſe to make thee a Miniſter and a witneſſe of the things which thou haſt ſeen, and of the things which ſhall appear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, delivering thee from the people and from the Gentiles unto whom now I ſend thee, to open their eyes, and to turn them from darknnſſe to light, and from the power of Satan unto God, that they may receive for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of ſins, and an Inheritance among them which are ſanctified by faith that is in me;</hi> and John 19.19. <hi>As thou haſt ſent me into the World, even ſo have I alſo ſent them into the World;</hi> Mind this Paſtor and People, Chriſt Jeſus was not ſent carnally to meddle with <hi>external things,</hi> touching the Redemption of ſouls, but <hi>he was in God Reconciling the world unto himſelf,</hi> preaching deliverance unto thoſe who was in captivity, and bringing the priſoner out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the ſeed from under the bondage and power of Satan, and ſaith he, <hi>as thou haſt ſent me into the world, ſo have I alſo ſent them into the world,</hi> and he prayed <hi>that they all might be one as the Father was one in him and he in him, that they all may be one in us, that the world might believe that thou haſt ſent me;</hi> mark, here is one cauſe of the unity, that the World might be convinced and believe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent him, and in the ſame meſſage is his Miniſters; But who can be convinced and believe by ſuch dark Paſtours as thou art, and you Teachers of the World generally are, who do not wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the unity with Chriſt and to be ſent by him onely, to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the work in the eternal, and not in the external which is temporal? And ſo you are manifeſt here by this Doctrine, that you are of the earth and firſt man in old <hi>Adams</hi> Tranſgreſſion; and ſo keeps people in the earth, in the letter and the corrupt, and this brings not people out of the darkneſſe into the light to ſit together <hi>with Chriſt Jeſus in the heavenly places,</hi> into the unity of the faith to be refreſhed together in Gods Spiritual Worſhip, nor
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36745:3"/>your Miniſtry brings not out of priſon but keeps in priſon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Chriſts, to which end the gifts was given by him who aſcended up on high, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>and gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, till all come to the unity of the Faith,</hi> which gives the victory over the World, ſo over ſin, contrary to your dark Miniſtry; and to this end was the gifts given to be Paſtors and Teachers, <hi>to perfect the Saints,</hi> which now all your carnal Sacraments and Rudiments cannot bring this to paſſe, <hi>viz.</hi> perfection in the Saints degree; Then come and let us reaſon with you, To what purpoſe is all your Ringing of Bells, dead prayers, dead Sermons, Bread and Wine, ſinging of <hi>Davids</hi> experiences, Baptizing with a little cold water, being all external things, which cannot bring to perfect the Saints. I ſay in the fear of the Lord conſider, what is all theſe to purpoſe, and wherein doth God require theſe things at your hands, ſeeing you have excluded or ſeparated your ſelves from Chriſts unity, and ſo your gifts are bought and ſold with mony, and may you not well be called the Merchants of <hi>Babylon?</hi> Therefore O Royal Seed where ever thou art, turn away from theſe, <hi>who through covetouſneſſe make merchandize of ſouls,</hi> and are evidently ſeparate by their life and Doctrine from the unity of Chriſt, and ſo from his Miniſtry, for I ſhew thee that firſt the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the light of Chriſt working mightily in them, delivers them from a people that ſits in darkneſſe and evil; And then in the time of his love gives the command to them as Miniſters, as he did to <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſpirit, when he delivered him from the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting ſtate and dark condition, he ſent him to this end, to open their eyes, <hi>and turn them from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan unto God, &amp;c.</hi> which now you Paſtors and Miniſters ſo called of <hi>Leeds,</hi> I charge you to give an account of this Teſtimony, <hi>viz.</hi> your deliverance from the evil, the pride, the covetouſneſſe, the envy, the drunkenneſſe, the laſciviouſneſſe, the feaſting of the Rich, and neglecting the poor, the envy and the wrath that is in the hearts of people, with all the works of the fleſh, and that you are Redeemed from theſe, and ſent by God in the ſpirit to them to ſpeak the mind of Chriſt, without coveting any mans gold or ſilver, or elſe be ſilent for ſhame, and come under the judgement, and firſt <hi>pluck the beam out of your own eye, and then you may ſee the evil that is in others,</hi> which bondages their ſouls, and ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36745:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>be profitable to them and not hurtful, till which be witneſſed you cannot fly from the judgement, but are the blind guides, and none but the blind are led by you; So I beſeech you in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of love be warned, and let the light in your own particulars ſearch you, Rent your hearts, and ſtrip you of every falſe cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; This is a falſe covering, for you to be named Miniſters of Chriſt, and your work onely <hi>external,</hi> This is a falſe covering for you to be called <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to lay on hands for the work of the <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> and call <hi>Elders,</hi> when you never came yet to the babes eſtate, to <hi>deſire the ſincere milk of the word, that you may grow thereby</hi> to become Elders in the Truth, whilſt you have been taking the letter for the Word, the Baptizing with outward water for the Baptiſm of Chriſt, to give the name Chriſtian, the Bread and Wine carnal for the Supper of Chriſt, and <hi>the Light of Chriſt which is able to ſave to the utmoſt all that come to God by him, the light,</hi> to be that of a natural conſcience, for the Scripture Records theſe to be in the power of the Spirit; Therefore ſearch the Scriptures and ſee whether theſe things be ſo, and you finding them thus, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of your forms, and come to Chriſt the Light who is the life of men, kiſſe him that judgeth, who is the Son of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, leaſt his wrath kindle ſpeedily againſt you, and you be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed from not being a people becauſe of diſobedience.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Martin Hyles</hi> who made this Priſon much-what to put the witneſſes of God in which teſtifie againſt deceit; Remember <hi>Hamans</hi> policy, wrath and envy againſt the upright-hearted <hi>Jew,</hi> and what did that avail him in the end, or was not he worſe for that and not better? Take heed, in the dread of God I warn thee to Repentance of thy paſt actions againſt the upright-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted who worſhip God in Spirit and Truth, the Righteous Seed, and let thy raſhneſſe be turned into moderation, and thy ſpirit of fury into love and meekneſſe. And if thou be a Magiſtrate, be glad to defend the Innocent, and let true Juſtice paſſe upon the workers of iniquity, for thats the Magiſtrates place, and this Greeting is to thee <hi>Martin Hyles</hi> from thy priſon-houſe, And to you all Rulers and Prieſts in and about this <hi>Leeds,</hi> who live in the fleſh, and worſhip not God in Spirit and Truth, lay aſide all ſuperfluity of naughtineſſe, and let the time paſt be ſufficient for you to have perſecuted the Innocent, and cauſe the People of God by Creation to erre, who as yet ſit in darkneſſe, by your lyes and lightneſſe, pride and vanity, many are yet under your
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36745:4"/>and kept in the Land of darkneſſe, as ſheep ſcattered <hi>in the darke and cloudy day,</hi> And your ſelves with the luſt of your own hearts keep the witneſſe under Deaths Dominion in the particular, And ſo may not the diſperſed of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſay what good can be expected from ſuch Teachers and Leaders who themſelves are in bondage to Satan the Prince of darkneſſe; may not a Lamentation be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up in the true Propheſie concerning this people, <hi>They build up Zion with blood and Jeruſalem with iniquity, the heads thereof judge for reward, and the Prieſts thereof teach for hire, the Prophets thereof Divine for money, yet will they lean upon the Lord and ſay, is not the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, none evil can come upon us,</hi> is not this your building, is not this your practiſe? O <hi>Leeds, England</hi> and <hi>New-England,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ceaſe from this wherein ye provoke the Lord to wrath, and let your right eye be put out as concerning this, and your hand wither and become dead as touching this, for what will it avail you to ſtrive againſt the ſtream; For the Lord to his People is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a place of <hi>Broad Rivers</hi> and ſtream of water, and if ever you come to Redemption you muſt be plowed as a field, and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Word of God from your blood-thirſtineſſe, pride, arrogancy and deceit, the workers of which cannot enter into the Kingdom of God: Therefore come to the feeling of the Juſt which tells you envy is of the Devil, pride and ſwelling words of vanity and the luſt of the eye is of the World, and not of the Father, and if any man love the World, the love of the Father is not in him, take counſel at the Spirit of God and weigh the thing, for this which expreſſeth unto thee in the love of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would not have your ſouls to periſh; So if you love your ſouls be obedient, and let not the enemy betray you through his wiſdom in keeping you from the ſence of the new Creature, and in that old <hi>Adams</hi> ſtate imagines there can be no due order as to Government and Worſhip (in the generation choſen out from you) but the living wiſdom is made manifeſt in the ſeparation from the Worlds Idolatry, in which ſtate our Officers ſhall be peace and our Exactors Righteouſneſſe, our Judges reſtored as at the firſt, and our Counſellors as at the beginning: So the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving order of Gods Spirit is not run from but witneſſed, <hi>And the Creature waits for the earneſt expectation of the Son of God, to be freed from the bondage of iniquity,</hi> and he is the Son of God, the Light of the World, whom all the Kingdoms of the earth muſt become his, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt who is of power, authority and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36745:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>to Rule over all with <hi>a Rod of iron,</hi> and this is that I would bring you up into, out of the carnal and deceit, wherein is the ſtrife, that in the obedience to the Juſt you may come into the enjoyment of Gods Righteouſneſs; And if you here contenin or ſpeak againſt this Government, the true ſword of the Spirit may be turned againſt you; ſo try your wayes and come out of the pit of deſtruction, that the life of Innocency you may feel, to partake of the Lambs mercy.</p>
            <p>And you friends who are of the Seed, convinced with the Juſt in your own particulars, and in ſtilneſſe, the light in your hearts diſcovers unto you the enmity of the unjuſt, and lets you ſee the evil of the World, the wickedneſſe of the times, ſo that whileſt ye are mingled with the heathen which worſhip not God in ſpirit and Truth, you are wrong, and the wrong is unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous which cannot inherit the Kingdom of God; Therefore O friends, joyn with the Righteous principle that diſcovers unto you the wrong, the unrighteous, and herein is the weight and the burthen felt which muſt be caſt off, that lets for running the race of holineſſe, and the command is grievous to the diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent but rejoycing to the Juſt, he is near, the light, to give thee ſtrength to come through the power of darkneſs in your own particulars, then the powers of darkneſſe without you will be as aſhes under the feet of the pure, and the living faith through your ſteadfaſt love to the Truth will encreaſe to purfie the heart and cleanſe your ſouls with the precious blood of <hi>the Lamb ſlain ſince the foundation of the World,</hi> and this friends the ſalvation of your ſouls is more precious than all the things of the earth; So in the love of God which would draw you unto him, and give you a manſion in his houſe, be faithful and valiant, and look not at the enemies advantages, which would draw from the leaſt ſimplicity of the Goſpel to uphold his kingdom which muſt be thrown down, and the pure Authority eſtabliſhed, ſo fly not that which is to bring near into Gods love, the Croſſe, the obedience unto Gods witneſſe, who waits to lead thee up to the Land of the living, hear his voyce, <hi>the Lamb of God which taketh away the ſins of the world,</hi> and look not at names or Reproaches, but count them Riches, and all names whatſoeuer the perſons being not in the nature of Chriſt, there is rottenneſſe in the bones, and not a ſweet ſavour unto God, which except Chriſt the life be witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the mortal body, the ſoul is under Deaths dominion; So
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36745:5"/>come forth &amp; partake with the ſufferings that thou mayeſt Reign with him in the glorious ſtate, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus the Prince of peace, whoſe banner of love is ſtretched forth to Redeem the captives of Iudah, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the preſerved of Iſrael,</hi> Glory, honour and everlaſting pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be given unto him by all the ſeed in whom ſin Reigns not in their mortal bodies, who are the ſaints of the moſt high God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Samuel Watſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
